Behold the mighty cockroach.
Believed to have originated in the Silurian
period over 350 million years ago,...
..they can be found in every part of
the world from the tropics to the Arctic.
There exists 4,000 known species,...
..and in a year a single female can produce...
..over half a million descendants.
Radiation doesn't kill them.
By evolutionary standards,
they are nearly flawless creatures,...
..but creatures nevertheless.
Possessing only a simple nervous system,...
..their behaviour is dictated solely
by responses to environmental stimuli.
Unlike us, they are incapable of thought,...
..of self-illumination.
Compared to the roach, we are gods,...
..and must therefore act accordingly.
Is it true if you decapitate them,
they continue to live,...
..eventually dying of starvation?
Look, buddy, I just kill 'em.
Well, that's why I called you.
I thought that nowadays
you froze the insects to death.
Freeze 'em? Where's the fun in that?
No, we got a new pesticide
that works like a fungus.
It not only kills the infected roach,
but that roach then spreads the disease...
..to every other roach
it comes into contact with.
Just as long as you get rid of them.
Bugs, you know,...
..they drive me crazy.
Why, you arrogant little...
I forgot to tell you, I also found a roach on...
(phone rings)
Mulder.
(Scully) I've been trying to reach you all day.
My apartment complex
was being fumigated
so I thought I'd get away for the weekend.
- I came up to Massachusetts.
- Visiting your mother?
No. Just sitting and thinking.
Accounts of unidentified coloured
lights hovering in the skies...
..were reported in this area last night.
Look, Scully, I know it's not your inclination,
but did you ever look up into the night sky...
..and feel certain that not only
was something up there,...
..but it was looking down on you
at that exact same moment,...
..and was just as curious about you
as you are about it?
The only thing more fortuitous than
the emergence of life on this planet...
..is that, through random laws
of biological evolution,...
..an intelligence as complex as ours
ever emanated from it.
The very idea of intelligent alien life
is not only astronomically improbable,...
..but at its most basic level
downright anti-DanNinian.
Scully, what are you wearing?
I understand what you're saying,
but ljust need to keep looking.
Yeah, well, don't look too hard.
You might not like what you find.
Isn't that what Dr Zaius said to Charlton
Heston at the end of Planet of the Apes?
And look what happened.
- Scully, I gotta go.
- What? Mulder, what's going on?
Mulder.
How ya doin'? What are you doin'?
- Just sitting, thinking.
- Sittin' and thinkin'.
And talkin' on the phone.
Who with, your drug dealer?
Let me see some ID.
The Bureau? You on a case?
I heard reports of several UFO sightings in
this area last night. Did you see anything?
No, sir, not personally.
But we did receive a lot of telephone calls.
- Any more calls tonight?
- No, sir.
The FBI keeps tabs on these things?
No.
I don't like to pry, but why are you
sitting here with your wiper blades on?
I was just knocking off
some bugs that landed on my...
- Landed on my windshield.
- Cockroaches?
Maybe. Maybe beetles. I don't know.
- I'm not really good with bugs.
- (radio) This is Despatch. Come in. Over.
- Sorry to disturb you, sir.
- What's the matter?
Another roach attack.
(phone rings)
- Hello.
- I think you better get up here.
What is it?
Cockroaches are mortally attacking people.
I'm not gonna ask you if you said what
I think you said. I know it's what you said.
I'm with a bug exterminator
whose recently deceased body...
..was discovered with cockroaches
crawling all over him.
The sheriff says two other bodies were
found in the same condition this afternoon.
Where are you again?
Miller's Grove.
It has a large science constituency.
The other incidents involved
a biologist and an astrophysicist.
The witness to this case
is an alternative-fuel researcher.
These reports are not coming from
yahoos out in the boondocks.
The image of those cockroaches has been
permanently imprinted onto my brain.
I see them every time I close my eyes.
Try not to close your eyes.
How am I gonna sleep?
And where?
I'm certainly not spending the night here.
Maybe you could get
a motel room or something.
- Were there insect bites on the body?
- Insect bites?
No.
Cos millions of people
are actually allergic to cockroaches.
There have been reported cases of fatal
reactions. It's called anaphylactic shock.
- Anaphylactic shock?
- Such reactions have occurred to...
..entomologists or exterminators.
- OK, we'll check that out.
- You still want me to come up?
No, no, no. I'm sure you're right.
Thanks, Scully.
- Who was that?
- My drug dealer.
Dude, that's some good crap.
Come on, it's your hoot.
- I don't know about this, you guys.
- You really ought to, you know. Try it.
This stuff takes your mind
and just sort of, you know, expands it.
Well, something tells me it's more than my
mind you guys are interested in expanding.
- Well, how about another beer, then?
- OK.
I don't know.
I think you're makin' a mistake here.
Beer is just, you know... beer.
But this stuff, it, like, swings
the doors of perception so wide open,...
..you can see
a whole nother world out there.
But it's still like this world, you know.
It tweaks your mind and does
this whole altered-state thing to it.
And suddenly you see reality as it,
you know,...
..really exists.
- Oh, God!
- Dude, what's wrong, man?
Oh, God!
- Roaches!
- Dude, you're freakin', man
Roaches! Cockroaches!
Stop it!
(phone rings)
Stay.
Hello?
I take it back. I think you better get up here.
- Another roach attack?
- This was no allergic reaction.
Two witnesses claim
they saw the victim screaming
about roaches burrowing into him.
- Are there insects in the body?
- We haven't located any.
- But there are wounds all over the body.
- From the cockroaches?
Well, the victim did attempt to extract
the insects using a razor blade.
We're not sure all the incisions are
self-inflicted, except for the severed artery.
- Was there any evidence of drug use?
- Well, he did have a home-made lab setup.
I'm not sure what he was producing.
Oh, man! It smells like a septic tank.
Will you make sure this gets analysed here?
There's a psychotic disorder
associated with some drug abuse,...
..where the abuser has delusions
that insects are infesting their epidermis.
- It's called Ekbom Syndrome.
- Ekbom Syndrome?
The victim cuts himself in an attempt
to extract the imaginary insect.
- You still want me to come up?
- No. You're probably right.
- I'm sorry to bother you.
- It's no bother.
Bye.
- (barking)
- Hey!
Braindead. Couldn't get anything out of 'em.
How about some urine?
For a drug test.
- Did you get it?
- Get me a container.
- I think I killed it.
- You didn't kill it. You annihilated it.
It must have moulted.
It's just empty exoskeleton.
At least we have evidence
that cockroaches were here.
We've got more than that, Sheriff. I think
that bug's exoskeleton was made of metal.
- Nothing more than a skin abrasion.
- Caused by a metallic substance?
Why don't we wait until the analysis
of the compound is finished...
..before jumping to any conclusions?
Agent Mulder, as a doctor, I always find it
best to be completely honest and open...
..with my patients,
no matter how unpleasant the information.
What do you need to tell me?
No, I need you to tell me something.
What the hell is going on here?
- Are we in any danger?
- I don't know.
- Well, should I evacuate my family?
- I wouldn't know.
They're waiting for you
to examine the boy's body.
Yeah, soon as I take a little break.
After talking with Agent Mulder here,
I suddenly feel slightly constipated.
What's his problem?
He's upset that I don't know
what's going on here.
So what the hell is goin' on here?
Just because I work for the government
doesn't mean I'm an expert on cockroaches.
You're saying you don't know anything
about the government's experiments here?
- Experiments?
- A Department of Agriculture agent...
..sets up base on
a couple of acres across town.
Nobody knows exactly what's
goin' on out there. It's top-secret.
- Very hush-hush.
- What are you suggesting?
Killer bees were a genetic
experiment gone awry.
Let loose on an unsuspecting populace.
Who's to say the government hasn't created
a new breed of killer cockroaches?
You might wanna keep that theory to
yourself, Sheriff. No need to create a panic.
(man) Oh! Oh, my God! Help!
Somebody help me!
- What the hell happened?
- Cockroaches.
- He was covered in cockroaches.
- I don't see any roaches.
Well, when I went out to look for help
and I came back, they'd disappeared.
Gently.
It doesn't appear odd in any...
Next time let me handle the roaches.
(phone rings)
Who died now?
The medical examiner. His body was found
next to a toilet covered with roaches.
- I really think you should come.
- A toilet?
Check his eyes. Is one of them bloodshot,
with a dilated pupil?
- Well, yeah.
- It was probably a brain aneurysm.
Brain aneurysm?
Straining too forcefully is very common
causation for bursting a brain aneurysm.
- How do you explain the roaches, though?
- Did you catch any?
- Almost.
- I don't know what to tell you, Mulder.
I just hope you're not implying you've come
across an infestation of killer cockroaches.
(phone rings)
- Mulder.
- Mulder, I've been doing some research.
In the '80s there was a cockroach species
previously only found in Asia.
Since then it's appeared in Florida. They've
now established themselves in this country.
- Do they attack people?
- No, but they're different than our breeds.
They fly long distances
and are attracted to light.
- Do they attack people?
- I'm suggesting that what's happening...
..might be the introduction of
a new species of cockroach,
one that is attracted to people.
That all makes perfect sense.
I don't like it at all.
Did you know that
the Federal Government has been...
..conducting secret experiments here?
You're not thinking of trespassing
onto government property?
- I know you've done it in the past, but I...
- It's too late. I'm already inside.
- Well, what's going on? What do you see?
- I'm in a house.
It's apparently empty.
- What does the place look like?
- It's a typical two-storey suburban house.
Nice big living room,
sparsely furnished, nice carpets, fireplace.
Nice kitchen, modern appliances.
- Moving walls.
- Moving walls?
Yeah.
They're rippling.
- Oh! Cockroaches!
- What?!
Cockroaches. They're everywhere!
Ugh! I'm surrounded.
- You've got to get out of there right now.
- No!
- Are you all right? What happened?
- Flashlight went out.
Mulder, what's going on?
Gotta go.
Mulder! Mulder!
May I ask why you're trespassing
on government property?
- I'm a federal agent.
-So am I
Agent Mulder, FBI.
Dr Berenbaum, USDA,
Agricultural Research Service.
Dr Berenbaum,
I'm gonna have to ask you a few questions.
For instance?
What's a woman like you
doing in a place like this?
By studying how insects respond
to changes in light, temperature,...
..air currents, food availability, we can
determine the best ways to eradicate them.
Why all the secrecy about your research?
You got the good townspeople suspicious.
You expect us to advertise that
we've intentionally infested a house...
..with thousands of cockroaches?
But those cockroaches,
are they a normal species?
They're a common one.
Have you ever come across a type of
cockroach that is attracted to people?
Most cockroaches have been known
to wash themselves
after being touched by humans.
So you've never seen an instance where
a cockroach attacks a human being?
There have been cases where cockroaches
crawled into a person's ear, nose...
Nose?
What is that there?
It's just a pet project of mine.
Since an insect's exoskeleton
is a dielectric...
..surrounding the conductive
medium of its body fluid,...
..when introduced into an electrical field,
the brush discharge results
in a coloured flare.
What is that supposed to prove?
Well, it's my theory that UFOs
are actually insect swarms.
I don't know if you know anything about
UFOs, but all the characteristics of...
..a typical sighting are shared
with nocturnal insects
swarming through an electrical field.
The sudden appearance of a coloured,
glowing light hovering in the night sky.
Moving in a non-mechanical manner,
possibly humming.
Creating interference with
radio and television signals,...
..then suddenly disappearing.
As... nocturnal insect swarms.
It's... it's fascinating.
Everything about insects is fascinating.
They are truly remarkable creatures.
So beautiful and so honest.
Honest?
Eat, sleep, defecate, procreate.
That's all they do.
That's all we do,
but at least insects don't kid themselves
that it's anything more than that.
Does my scientific detachment disturb you?
No. No, actually, I find it quite refreshing.
(phone rings)
Not now. You know, um...
..I have always found insects
to be very interesting.
Really?
This is the fifth report of a deceased body
found amongst a horde of cockroaches,...
..but police are not confirming - yet -
that the insects have anything to do
with the fatalities.
Police have denied that these deaths
were the result of an outbreak...
..of the Ebola virus somehow being
spread by infected cockroaches.
For now these incidents remain
under local jurisdiction, . ..
..but a nurse here did confirm
that an FBI agent is on the case.
Police are asking that if you see
any cockroaches, don 't panic.
Simply notify the local authorities
and evacuate the area immediately.
Reporting live,
this is Sky Lathan for Channel 3 News.
Then suddenly there was this terrible crash.
You know, you could have been killed.
- (phone rings)
- Mulder, are you OK?
- I can't sleep.
- What happened at the USDA site?
They're conducting legitimate experiments.
I met an entomologist, a Dr Berenbaum,...
..who agrees with your theory of
an accidental importation of a new species.
Did he tell you how to catch 'em?
No, but she did tell me everything else
there is to know about insects.
She?
Yeah. Did you know the ancient Egyptians
worshipped the scarab beetle...
..and maybe erected the pyramids to honour
them, which may be symbolic dung heaps?
Did you know the inventor of the
flush toilet was named Thomas Crapper?
- Bambi has a theory I've never come across.
- Who?
- Dr Berenbaum. Anyway, her theory is...
- Her name is Bambi?
Yeah, both her parents were naturalists.
Her theory is that UFOs are nocturnal insect
swarms passing through electrical airfields.
- Her name is Bambi?
- Scully, can I confess something to you?
- Yeah, sure, OK.
- I hate insects.
You know, lots of people are
afraid of insects, Mulder. It's just...
- It's a natural instinct of...
- No, no, no, I'm not afraid of them.
I hate them.
One day back when I was a kid,
I was climbing this tree...
..when I noticed this leaf
walking towards me.
- It took me for ever to realise it was no leaf.
- A praying mantis?
Yeah, I had a praying-mantis epiphany,
and as a result I screamed.
Not a girlie scream, but the scream
of someone being confronted...
..by some before-unknown monster that had
no right existing on the same planet.
Did you ever notice how a praying mantis's
head resembles an alien's head?
The mysteries of the natural world
were revealed.
Instead of being astounded, I was...
..repulsed.
Mulder, are you sure
it wasn't a girlie scream?
- (man screams)
- What was that?
- I gotta go.
- Mul... No...
- Did you hear that too?
- It came from over here.
What the hell's goin' on?
Hello?
Is everything all right in there?
(screams)
(phone rings)
- What happened this time?
- One of the motel guests died.
Mulder, I'm coming up there right now.
Scully, I think this man died simply from
a reaction to the cockroaches.
Two cases of anaphylactic shock
in the same day in the same town
is highly improbable.
I'm saying that this man
simply had a heart attack.
Word about the cockroach infestation
and the deaths related to it has gotten out.
I think this man simply saw some
cockroaches and scared himself to death.
Regardless, something strange
is definitely going on up there.
Maybe not.
All your conjectures have proved correct.
The exterminator did die
from anaphylactic shock.
The boy did die from self-inflicted wounds...
..and was getting high off methane fumes
derived from burning manure.
The medical examiner
did die from a brain aneurysm.
I still haven't been able
to explain the cockroaches.
Or the fact that their
exoskeletons are made of metal.
Metal? What are you talking about?
Mulder?
- Mulder, I'm coming up there.
- Whatever.
- Can you tell what kind of cockroach it is?
- I should be able to.
The abdomen's still attached and we
differentiate species by their genitalia.
- Oh, my God.
- Is it abnormal?
I'll say. He's hung like
a club-tailed dragonfly! Excuse me.
- Does it still look unusual?
- Well, yes. For an insect genitalia.
But maybe not for a microprocessor.
You're implying that
this insect is mechanical?
What am I supposed to be looking at here?
Have you ever seen
anything like this before?
Only in science journals. I've read about
an artificial-intelligence researcher...
..who designs robots that resemble
and behave like insects.
I've never seen them,
but I've often thought of visiting his lab.
He works out of this town?
- Dr Ivanov?
- Why are you scaring my robots?
For decades my colleagues
in artificial intelligence...
..have attempted to create
an autonomous robot.
By struggling to give their machines
a humanlike brain, they have failed.
A human brain is too complex.
Too computational. It thinks too much.
But insects merely react.
I've used insects as my model,
not just in design,...
..but by giving them the simplest
of computer programs:
"Go to the object."
"Go away from moving object."
Governed only by sensors
and reflex responses,...
..they take on the behaviour
of intelligent living beings.
So this is programmed
to head towards any object...
..moving within the field of its sensors?
No.
Then why is it following me?
It likes you.
Your contract is with NASA?
The goal is to transport a fleet
of robots to another planet...
..and allow them to navigate
the terrain with more intricacy...
..than any space probe has done before.
And it sounds slightly fantastic,
but the only obstacle I can foresee...
..is devising a renewable energy source.
In any case,
this is the future of space exploration.
It does not include living entities.
I'm just speculating,
but if extraterrestrial life forms do exist...
No need for speculation. I believe they do.
If they're technologically advanced,
and if your ideas about the future...
- ..of space exploration are correct...
- The interplanetary explorers...
..of alien civilisations will likely
be mechanical in nature. Yes.
Anyone who thinks alien visitation
will come not in the form of robots...
..but of living beings
with big eyes and grey skin...
..has been brainwashed
by too much science fiction.
- Can you identify this?
- I'm not really good with bugs.
- A cricket's leg?
- Try it under the microscope.
Are you all right, Dr Ivanov?
Can you identify that?
Sir?
It's... beyond my comprehension.
Hey, kid! Move it!
Let go,buddy!
Get back in the car!
- (man) Hey, what are you, crazy?
- (woman) Hey, you idiot! You hit me!
Excuse me. Do you sell road maps?
Could you tell me where they are?
- Come on. Hurry up.
- What's going on here?
Haven't you heard about the roaches?
They're devouring people.
We're getting outta here.
- Have you seen any yourself?
- No, but they're everywhere.
Roaches aren't attacking people. They're
spreading the Ebola virus. Keep the change.
We're all gonna be bleeding
from our nipples.
All right. Listen up! I'm Agent Dana Scully
from the Federal Bureau of Investigation.
I am assuring you that
you are not in any danger.
Everything is gonna be OK if you just
calm down and start acting rationally.
Now where the hell are those road maps?
Hey! This last can is mine!
Roaches!
Well, Doctor, I... I appreciate you taking
the time to... answer my questions.
Yeah.
Greetings from planet Earth.
Well, it's a cockroach all right.
It's not like the leg segment
you had me examine earlier.
- It's just a typical cockroach.
- Even the...
Yes, even the genitalia's normal.
Cockroaches are common
in this area this time of year.
It's one of the reasons
I set up my study here.
(phone rings)
- Mulder.
- Mulder, this town is insane.
- Where are you?
- In a convenience store on the outskirts of...
..civilisation.
Look, I think I may have a lead.
Remember Dr Eckerle,...
..the alternative-fuel researcher
that witnessed the exterminator's death?
Well, the fuel that he's researching
is methane gas.
- Methane derived from manure.
- Manure?
He has an import licence to bring in animal
dung samples from outside the country.
Now, maybe you can confirm this
with your Dr Bambi,...
..but I think the cockroaches
are dung eaters,...
..and, if so, some of them
may have been shipped accidentally
in some of the samples.
This fuel research facility could be
ground zero for the infestation.
If an alien civilisation were technologically
advanced enough to build and send...
..artificially intelligent
robotic probes to space,...
..might they not have been able to perfect
the extraction of methane fuel
from manure,...
..a replenishing energy source on a planet
filled with dung-producing creatures?
- I think you've been in this town too long.
- Where's the research facility located?
Bambi, you better wait here
until I make sure it's safe.
Be careful. We don't know what
these cockroaches are capable of.
If they're even cockroaches.
I'm more worried about the human element.
(gunshot)
Dr Eckerle?
They're after me.
First at my house. Then at the motel.
And then I came here to get away.
But... they're following me.
You're not in any danger.
They won't harm you.
- I've seen them kill two men.
- They weren't responsible for those deaths.
But they might be responsible for ours
if you fire your gun
in a plant full of methane gas.
Don't you understand?
The bugs,...
..they drive me crazy.
Let me guess. Bambi.
Fox told me to wait out here
while he checked inside first.
Should I come along with you?
No.
This is no place for an entomologist.
Why are these roaches
making those weird noises?
In Madagascar the roaches hiss by blowing
air through holes in their upper thorax.
Really?
- How do you know so much about them?
- I don't.
That's why we shouldn't kill these
but capture them for further study.
Put the gun down.
- Have I lost my mind?
- No.
You've had a very stressful day
that's affected your ability to think clearly.
Your judgment is a little clouded right now.
It is?
Then how do I know
that you're not a cockroach?
Mulder?
Mulder!
I assure you, Dr Eckerle,
I'm just as human as you are. If not more so.
(phone rings)
You are one of them!
- Mulder!
- Get out! This whole place could blow!
Get down!
Crap.
It's like a crematorium. I don't think
we're gonna locate the doctor's remains.
- Or anything else for that matter.
- It's not as bad as some of the other fires.
- There were others?
- Four, to be exact.
Plus 18 automobile accidents, 13 assault
and batteries, two stores were looted.
36 injuries all total,
half of 'em from insecticide poisoning.
But we didn't receive reports
on cockroaches
or otherwise for the last couple of hours.
Maybe this town's
finally come to its senses.
You two oughta go home and get some rest.
You look pooped.
Agent Mulder!
They told me I could locate you here.
Those segments you showed me earlier -
may I examine them again?
Well, they're completely desiccated.
Just like the moulted exoskeleton.
Many insects don't develop wings
until their last moulting stage.
Perhaps these things had their final moult...
..and have flown off back
to wherever they originated.
- Yeah, that would explain everything(!)
- May I borrow this for further study?
I've already had a similar sample analysed.
It's nothing but common metals.
- What do you hope to find from it?
- His destiny.
Isn't that what Dr Zaius said to Zira
at the end of the Planet of the Apes?
- It's one of my favourite movies.
- Mine too.
I love science fiction.
I'm also fascinated by your research.
Have you considered
programming your robots...
..to mimic behaviour
of social insects like ants or bees?
As a matter of fact, I have.
You know, I read...
Smart is sexy.
Think of it this way.
By the time there's another invasion...
..of artificially intelligent,
dung-eating robotic probes,...
..maybe their Uberchildren will have
devised a way to save our planet.
You know,
I never thought I'd say this to you, Scully,...
..but you smell bad.
Our cerebral cortex
is the greatest achievement...
..of the evolutionary processes. Big deal.
While allowing us intellect
and self-consciousness,...
..it is all too often overruled
by our inner instinctive brain:
the one that tells us to react, not reflect,
to run rather than ruminate.
Maybe we have gone as far as
we can go, and the next advance,...
..whatever that may be, will be made
by beings we create using our own tech...
(beep)
- ..tech...
- (beep)
..technology. Life forms we can
design and program not to be...
..ultimately governed and
constricted by the rules of survival.
Perhaps that step has already
been achieved on another planet...
..by organisms that had
a billion years' head start on us.
If these beings ever visited us,
would we recognise what we were seeing?
And would they react
in anything but horror...
..at seeing such mindless,
primitive, hideous creatures?
Visiontext Subtitles: Sally Lewis
(child) I made this!